# Alexandros FILOTHEOU

Thessaloniki GR  $\cdot$  alexandros.filotheou@gmail.com  $\cdot$  (+30) 693 8787 677  $\cdot$  linkedin.com/in/alexandros-filotheou github.com/li9i  $\cdot$  Portfolio

Senior Robotics Engineer specialising in the full product lifecycle, from concept and simulation to continuous system integration and field deployment. Experience of 9+ years in integration, state estimation, sensor fusion, SLAM, localisation, autonomous navigation, control, perception, computer vision, and hardware. Delivered 50% improvement in localisation accuracy for a fleet of RFID-tag inventorying robots, enabling centimeter precision in tag-pinpointing. Proven ability to materialise research and bridge it with real-world development and deployment to deliver reliable systems with repeatable behaviours.

## Skills

English Native / Fluent (IELTS 8.5 - C2 Proficiency)
Languages C/C++, Python, shell, MATLAB/Octave

Robotics/OS Linux, ROS/ROS 2

Tools/Frameworks git, Docker, Eigen, Behavior Trees, Gazebo, CI/CD, Qt/Tkinter, OpenCV

Control Techniques MPC, PID, LQR

# Experience

#### Robotics Software Engineer · ITI-CERTH, Thessaloniki GR

Sep 2023 – Present

- Owner of software integration and git repository maintainer in EU-funded R&D project RoBétArmé
- Determined development and deployment principles for 9 partners and >50 Dockerised ROS packages
- Orchestrated fleet of concrete- and metal-additive manufacturing robots with Behaviour Trees
- Identified bottlenecks and reduced deployment time >10x across fleet by utilising tmux features
- Ensured code quality via googletest and cpplint, continuous integration/deployment via CI/CD pipelines
- $\bullet \ \ \text{Achieved robust ROS-ROS 2 interoperability and communication across multiple machines using Zenoh}$

Robotics & Control Engineer · ECE dept., Aristotle University of Thessaloniki GR Sep 2018 – Mar 2023

- Technical Leader of robotics division in large-scale R&D projects RELIEF and CultureId
- Developed and deployed autonomous ground and aerial platforms in libraries, museums, and outdoors
- Boosted RFID-tag localisation accuracy by >3x by robustifying LiDAR-based filtering via Fourier analysis
- Deployed human-robot applications engaging 2,000+ visitors annually since 2023 at the AMTh museum
- Delivered production-grade 2D/3D SLAM and collision-avoiding navigation pipelines with intuitive user GUIs using Qt, teb planner, rtabmap, and karto
- Developed and integrated codebases for 18+ publications in top-tier IEEE journals/conferences, enabling multi-team experiments, translating novel robotics and RFID research to real-world solutions

 $\textbf{Teaching Assistant} \cdot \text{KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm SE}$ 

Sep 2016 – Nov 2016

• DD2380 - Artificial Intelligence under Prof. Patric Jensfelt

# Volunteering

### Computer Vision Engineer · PANDORA Robotics, Thessaloniki GR

Oct 2013 - Jul 2014

• Increased rescue probabilities by developing a C++ wall-hole detection system using Microsoft Kinect RGB-D in the international RoboCup Rescue competition, gaining  $2^{nd}$  place in 2015

## Links

## Education

Doctorate · Electrical & Computer Engineering · Aristotle University of Thessaloniki

Master of Science · Systems, Control, and Robotics · KTH Royal Inst. of Technology

Diploma · Electrical & Computer Engineering · Aristotle University of Thessaloniki

Sep 2018 – Jun 2023

Sep 2015 – Jun 2017

Sep 2005 – Jul 2013

### References

- Antonis Dimitriou · Coordinator of R&D projects · (+30) 697 88 96 350 · antodimi@auth.gr
- A complete list of professional references comprising supervisors and colleagues may be found at

github.com/li9i/cv/tree/master/references